Guide to the Issei Oral History Project in Watsonville Collection ARS.0081
Archive of Recorded Sound
Issei Oral History Project in Watsonville Collection
1978-1983
ARS.0081
Nakane, Kazuko
3 boxes: 37 audiocassettes; 15 folders of transcripts
Archive of Recorded Sound
The Issei Oral History Project in Watsonville was created by historian Kazuko Nakane in preparation for the book Nothing Left in my Hands: The Issei of a Rural California Town, 1900-1942. Interviews were conducted by Nakane from 1978 to 1983 with fifteen Japanese-American residents in Watsonville, California. The collection contains the original audiocassettes of these interviews and their transcripts in English.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The Issei Oral History Project in Watsonville Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Kazuko Nakane in 2009.
Scope and Contents
The Issei Oral History Project in Watsonville was created by historian Kazuko Nakane in preparation for the book Nothing Left in my Hands: The Issei of a Rural California Town, 1900-1942. Interviews were conducted in Japanese by Nakane from 1978 to 1983 with fifteen Japanese-American residents in Watsonville, California. Located in the Pajaro Valley, Watsonville and the surrounding area is overwhelmingly agricultural, and farming is a major topic discussed in the interviews. Other subjects include the impact of anti-immigration legislation, relocation camps during World War II, and the difficulty in maintaining relations with family still in Japan. The collection contains the original audiocassettes of these interviews, as well as transcripts in English.
Bibliography
Nakane, Kazuko. Nothing Left In My Hands: the Issei of a Rural California Town, 1900-1942. Berkeley, Calif.: Heyday Books, 2008.
Indexing Terms
Immigrants--California--Watsonville--Interviews; Japanese Americans--California--Watsonville--Interviews; Oral history
- 1. Audiocassettes, 1978-03-29 - 1983-02-10; 37 audiocassettes; Nakane, Kazuko
  - 1. Yoshito and Kimiyo Kadotani, 1978-05-29; Kadotani, Kimiyo; Kadotani, Yoshito
    Summary of conversation
    Interview of Yoshito Kadotani and his wife, Kimiyo Kadotani. It is mostly a biography of Yoshito, with brief contributions from Kimiyo. Yoshito Kadotani was born in July 10, Meiji 36 [1903] in Yashiro, Oshima-cho, Oshima-gun, Yamaguchi Prefecture to Taro Kadotani (father) and Hanako Kadotani (mother). (Names given as First name, Last name.)
    Yoshito came to the United States with his mother when he was 4 years old to join his father, who worked as a gardener in Watsonville, CA. Yoshito's family relocated to Santa Cruz when he was 5 years old, and has lived there ever since. Yoshito has two younger sisters and a younger brother, who were all born in Santa Cruz, CA.
    Yoshito's younger sister, Kiyoko Okahara is married and lives in Japan. Yoshito's younger brother, Kiyotaka Kadotani, is in the United States. Yoshito's youngest sister, Mieko Fujimura, is also in United States. From age 6, Yoshito attended Laurel Elementary School in Santa Cruz until he returned to Japan at the age of 10. He came back to United States when he was 19 years old in 1921 and graduated from Santa Cruz High School on Walnut Avenue in 1925.
    There are 24-25 Japanese families in Santa Cruz around this time. There was a correspondent who wrote a column about Watsonville in the ""Shinsekai"" newspaper in San Francisco. His name was Samonji Takeda.
    Yoshito started as a gardener, then worked as a landscape designer. On Feb. 22, 1942, with the United States at war with Japan, Yoshito was taken into custody by the FBI, the head of the local police department and a sergeant who came to Yoshito's house in Santa Cruz.
    Yoshito was the clerk of the Japanese Association in Santa Cruz at that time.
    The head of the Japanese Association in Santa Cruz, Mr. Tsumoru Kai, was also taken into custody. Yoshito's younger brother, Kiyotaka, who was visiting Mr. Kai by chance, was also taken into custody but later released since he had citizenship. From Santa Cruz, Yoshito was sent to North Dakota, then Louisiana, then Santa Fe, New Mexico.
    During his time in Camp Livingston, Louisiana, he met Kazuo Sakamaki, who is famous as the first prisoner of war. In the Santa Fe camp, Yoshito applied to join a road work project in Idaho and was accepted. After a hearing, he was released in April 1943 and returned to Arizona, where his sisters and brother were living. He then went to Chicago to work at the Family Welfare Office of the local internment camp. He returned to Santa Cruz after the war.
    Yoshito married Kimiyo in March 12, 1949. They have two adopted daughters. He received his U.S. citizenship on Feb. 14, 1956.
    Fujimura, Mieko; Kadotani, Hanako; Kadotani, Kathleen Kazuko; Kadotani, Kotaro; Kadotani, Shizutaka; Okahara, Kiyoko; Sakamaki, Kazuo; Chicago (Ill.); Livingston (La.); North Dakota; Santa Cruz (Calif.); Santa Fe (N.M.); Watsonville (Calif.); Ōshima-gun (Yamaguchi-ken, Japan)
    - Interview, May 29, 1978, 1978-05-29; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, May 29, 1978: Interviewee's Copy, 1978-05-29; 1 audiocassette
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 1)
  - 2. Shizuko Kajihara, 1978-04-30; Kajihara, Shizuko
    Mrs. Shizuko Kajihara was born on May 25, 1906 (Meiji 39) in Kure city, Hiroshima prefecture. She was raised by a relative on her mother’s side since her mother died when she was 6 years old. She came to the United States on Feb. 4, 1924, soon after her marriage in Japan. She arrived in San Francisco and came down to Los Angeles on the Tenyo-maru. She lived near LA with her husband and his parents. Her husband was growing vegetables. Mr. Kajihara was born in 1900 and came to the United States in 1916 since his father called for him. His father went back to Japan to bring his wife and Mr. Kajihara’s brother to the United States. Mr. Kajihara returned to Japan in the fall of 1923 to get married. It was an arranged marriage by Mrs. Kajihara’s uncle’s uncle. Mrs. Kajihara was only 17 years old when they got married on Nov. 24, 1923. In LA, they borrowed the name of a Japanese who had U.S. citizenship to rent 30-35 acres of land, on which they grew tomatoes and lettuce. Their oldest daughter is Yasuko, who was born on November 12, 1925 and currently lives in LA. Their second daughter, Teruko, passed away on May 24, 1972 due to acute pneumonia. Their oldest son, Eiji, died when he was 2 ½ years old. Their second son, George, was born in November, 1932. Their 3rd daughter, Setsuko, was born on July 27, 1935. She passed away when she was 4 years and 9 months old. Their 3rd son, Bill, was born on July 2, 1939, and lives in Watsonville. Their 4th son, Ronald (Masao is his Japanese name), was born Feb. 16, 1942. Their youngest daughter, Sandra (her Japanese name is Toshiko), was born in camp on July 25, 1945, and is a nurse in San Jose. Their 5th son, Robert, was born Feb. 26, 1948, and lives in Texas. They moved to Camp #1 in Poston, Arizona on May 17, 1942. Mr. Kajihara worked as a cook during this time. After camp, they stayed in Glendale, Arizona for a year then moved to Texas and farmed in Presidio in the lowlands. They cultivated cantaloupe in the summer. They came to Watsonville at the end of July 1953 and worked on a strawberry farm. Mr. Kajihara died in 1972.
    Hattori, Kathy; Kajihara, Bill; Kajihara, Eiji; Kajihara, George; Kajihara, Robert; Kajihara, Sandra Toshiko; Kajihara, Setsuko; Kajihara, Teruko; Kajihara, Yasuko; Glendale (Ariz.); Kure-shi (Japan); Poston (Ariz.); Presidio County (Tex.); San Jose (Calif.)
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 2)
  - 3. Anonymous, 1978-05-07
    This is a biographical interview with an male interviewee who specially asks the interviewer to keep his name anonymous in the book the interviewer is working on.
    The interviewee's wife joins the interview as a bystander half way through.
    The intervieweew as born in Meiji 32 [1899] in Kuga-gun, Yamaguchi Prefecture. He came to the United States to join his parents, who were cultivating strawberries in Watsonville, in 1914, when he was 15 years old. He has a younger sister and a younger brother, who were both born in Watsonville. He worked as a houseboy for a year, then helped on his father’s farm. A friend in Watsonville arranged a meeting between him and his wife’s sister, who lived in Japan. In 1922, he went to Japan to meet her, and they decided to marry. Her family is from Iwakuni-shi, Yamaguchi Prefecture. He was 22 years old, and his wife was 18 at the time of their marriage. In October 1922, their first son was born. Two years later, their daughter was born. He began his own farming business at the age of 25, growing lettuce in Watsonville. He saw Yoshie Fujiwara, the famous tenor singer, perform at Toyo Hall at 55 Union Street. He also saw Hibari Misora perform there. His first-born son is in the U.S. Army stationed in Hawaii. His first-born daughter is married to a farmer named Obata and lives in Gilroy. Their second daughter is in accounting. He was sent to Camp #1 in Poston, Arizona, then to Salinas camp in April 1942, and released in September 1945. He remembers his camp director very fondly. Camp #1 was overcrowded. He worked as a foreman of a road construction crew. His wife worked at the kitchen. His son was drafted, and in order to avoid fighting Japan, he went to Military Language School after his six months of Army training. Later, he went to the Philippines as a translator. Upon release from camp, he worked in Monterey’s Cannery Row.
    Fujiwara, Yoshie; Misora, Hibari; Iwakuni-shi (Japan); Poston (Ariz.)
    - Interview, May 7, 1978, 1978-05-07; 1 audiocassette (Audio 1, Cassette 3)
    - Interview, May or June, 1978, 1 audiocassette (Audio 1, Cassette 4)
    - Transcripts, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 3)
  - 4. Tokushige Kizuka, 1983-02-10; Kizuka, Tokushige
    Mr. Kizuka interview Tokushige Kizuka was born on May 22, Meiji 34 (1901) in Yasu-mura, Asakura-gun, Fukuoka prefecture to Tokube(macron) Kizuka (father) and mother. His parents left Japan to live in Watsonville, CA when Mr. Kizuka was six years old. His parents had an apple orchard with Mr. Matasaburo Mine, his brother-in-law. Mr. Kizuka lived with his grandmother and a younger sister. Mr. Kizuka joined his parents at the age of 17 in 1917 on board of Tenryu-maru, arriving at San Francisco, then went through immigration process for three days at the immigration office in Angel Island. His younger sister had passed away by then. He worked at his father’s apple orchard. He was married in 1923. He was married his relative (not blood-related) and has one son and one daughter. He began managing his own lettuce farm in 1927, after purchasing his own land right around 1926 or 1927, as he was certain he would not go back to Japan. Since he had to sign the lease, he hired a local lawyer (Mr. Son, Mr. Hogan) who he remembers very fondly. He became active in the Japanese Association around 1929. He build a Japanese School in his property which lasted right before his evacuation during the war. His farm was managed by his children and his wife while he was in the camp. Mr. Kizuka was a member of “Heimushakai”, which is called as “Hoshikai” in Watsonville. He was taken to the internment camp since he was a member of kendo.
    TAPE2: He applied his citizenship after it was allowed in 1952. His brother-in-law, who was a commissioned officer in the Japanese army, encouraged his return to Japan, and his parents suggested to send Mr. Kizuka’s children to Japan to get educated there, Mr. Kuzuka had no intention of separating from his children; he did not want to his children raised without own parents like he did.
    Kizuka, Tokube; Mine, Matasaburo; Angel Island (Calif.); Asakura-gun (Japan); Yasu-machi (Fukuoka-ken, Japan)
    - Interview, February 10, 1983, 1983-02-10; 2 audiocassettes
    - Interview, February 10, 1983: Interviewee's Copy, 1983-02-10; 2 audiocassettes
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 4)
  - 5. Shuro and Masa Kobayashi, 1978-03-29 and 1978-04-17; Kobayashi, Masa; Kobayashi, Shuro
    Mr. Shuro Kobayashi was born Nov. 25, 1886. His family owned a dry goods store (gofukuya) called Aburaya in Shimotsuma-shi, Ibaraki prefecture. Mr. Kobayashi was the youngest son. He had two sisters and three brothers. Two brothers came to the United States. His oldest brother, Kyutaro Nakamura, was adopted by another family. The second brother’s name is Minekichi Kobayashi, and the third is Eizo Kobayashi. His brother-in-law, a member of the Ibaraki prefectural assembly, called him “Shuro” (守郎).
    Mr. and Mrs. Kobayashi had just celebrated their 62nd wedding anniversary three days prior to the second interview.
    Mrs. Masa Kobayashi (maiden name: Kujirai) is from Shimotsuma-shi, Ibaraki prefecture and comes from a family of well-to-do landowners. Mrs. Kobayashi was sent to Tokyo for her education. Her father later lost his fortune in the stock market.
    Hattori, Kathy; Koga, Sumio, Rev.; Shimotsuma-shi (Japan)
    - Interview, March 29, 1978: Interviewee's Copy, 1978-03-29; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, April 17, 1978: Interviewee's Copy, 1978-04-17; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, March 29, 1978, 1978-03-29; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, April 17, 1978, 1978-04-17; 1 audiocassette
    - Transcripts, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 5)
  - 6. Hoy Lew, 1982-05-05; Lew, Hoy
    Interview condcuted at interviewee’s home. The entire interview was conducted in English. Margaret (Mr. Hoy Lew’s wife) was also there and sometimes assisted with the interview.
    Hoy was born in Taishan county, Guangdong, China. Birthday: Sept. 29, 1896. At the time of the interview, he was 85 years old. Hoy came to the United States in Dec. 1912 at the age of 16. He arrived in San Francisco and stayed on Angel Island for 11 days. Hoy thinks he was lucky, since he knows many people who had to stay on Angel Island much longer than that, some as long as a year. Hoy came to the United States with his father, who had been living in the United States but went back to China to bring Hoy with him. Mother was still in China, and joined them in the United States later. Hoy has three brothers and one sister. His old brother was already in the United States. His sister and two younger brothers were still in China. They all came later to the United States, and eventually Hoy had his entire family with him. Hoy hasn’t been back to China since. Hoy moved to Watsonville in 1913 after staying in San Francisco for a few months. When Hoy came to Watsonville, there were only about ten Chinese families there. Hoy’s father had a grocery store that supplied Chinese groceries to the community. Hoy’s father’s grocery store was among the few of its kind. Hoy worked at his father’s store. In the Watsonville and Aromas area, there were about 20 apple-drying plants owned by Chinese people.
    About Hoy’s experience at the apple-drying plant. They gathered second-grade (bruised) apples from apple-packing plants.During 1920-23, due to the depression, more than half of the small apple-drying businesses closed.
    About the gambling house/ Hoy doesn’t know much about the gambling house, nor the prostitution houses. He talks about how the Chinese community shifted from farming to owning small businesses such as grocery stores.
    He received his US citizenship after WWII.
    Angel Island (Calif.); San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.); Taishan Xian (Guangdong Sheng, China); Watsonville (Calif.)
    - Interview, May 5, 1982, 1982-05-05; 1 audiocassette
  - 7. Charles Leong, 1982-04-15; Leong, Charles
    The interviewee, Charles Leong, describes the history of downtown Watsonville, CA. Mr. Leong was born September 4, 1911 in San Francisco. His parents are from China. They moved from Oakland to Watsonville when he was 4-6 yrs old. They lived on Corralitos Road. Mr. Leong stayed in Watsonville until 1929, when he was 17. His family worked at the apple drying plants. Chinese gambling houses were big businesses in Watsonville and he used to go there at night.
    Chao, Vincent
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 6)
  - 8. Miteru Mano, 1978-05-05 and 1978-05-10; Mano, Miteru
    Mrs. Miteru Mano was born Meiji 26 (1893). Mr. Kojiro Mano was born in 1886. Mr. Kojiro Mano was working in a produce store in Fresno, CA and passed away in 1956. Mrs. Mano came to the United States when she was 21 years old. She didn’t receive any formal education in Japan. She is 86 years old at the time of the interview. Her maiden name was Matsuo, and she was from a farming family in Tamana-gun, Kumamoto prefecture. She had four brothers and a sister. Mrs. Mano was the only member of her family who came to the United States. She did so via an arranged marriage as a so-called “picture bride.” As Mr. Mano was already in the United States, Mrs. Mano traveled alone. After joining her husband, the two picked grapes in San Luis Obispo, where they had five boys and five girls. They were sent to camp in Tule Lake, CA for three years. They were allocated for four rooms and she recollects no hardship during this period. After being released from camp, they went to Fresno, CA.
    Hattori, Kathy; Mano, Kojiro; Fresno (Calif.); Tamana-shi (Japan)
    - Interview, May 5, 1978, 1978-05-05; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, May 10, 1978, 1978-05-10; 1 audiocassette
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 7)
  - 9. Chizu Matsuoka, 1982-05-04; Matsuoka, Chizu
    Mrs. Chizu Matsuoka was born in Kurouhara, Sente Village, Kaho-gun in Fukuoka Prefecture on February 16, 1902. Mr. Matsuoka’s father-in-law and her father are cousins. She received an education equivalent to present-day junior high school in Japan. After graduation, she left for Hakata and worked as an apprentice nurse at a hospital in Fukuoka-shi during the day. She took classes to be a midwife at night. After passing the test to be a midwife, she began working as an apprentice nurse in the hospital at a Mitsubishi coal mine. After she passed the test to become a nurse, her future husband came back from the United States and they got married. She was 23 years old then. It was a rather late age for a woman to marry in those days. Since they were relatives, their marriage was arranged by their parents before her future husband came back. In order to avoid the draft in Japan, they hurried to get married and left for the U.S. at the end of January or beginning of February, 1924. Mrs. Matsuoka’s husband, Tonai Matsuoka, was born November 15, 1892 (Meiji 25). He also finished his kotoka education in Japan. He was called by his parents in 1908 at the age of 16 to the United States. In Watsonville, Tonai operated “Yokohama Laundry” on Main Street in partnership with other Japanese. Mrs. Matsuoka received a license to be a midwife in 1925. She was the only Japanese among the examinees. She opened a maternity hospital at her house. Mr. and Mrs. Matsuoka had two children. At the time of the war, they were 15 and 12 years old. They were all sent to Camp #2 in Poston, Arizona. She worked as a doctor’s assistant in the camp. They came back to Watsonville in 1945, where Mr. Matsuoka started a gardening business. Both of them received citizenship around 1954 or 1955.
    Matsuoka, Tonai; Kaho-gun (Japan); Poston (Ariz.)
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 8)
  - 10. Kumajiro and Fuji Murakami, 1978-05; Murakami, Fuji; Murakami, Kumajiro
    The interviewees are Mr. Kumajiro Murakami and Mrs. Fuji Murakami. Mr. Kumajiro Murakami was born March 3, 1881 to a farming family in Saga-mura, Yamaguchi prefecture. He left Japan at the age of 17, and lived in Hawaii for five years. He had seven brothers and sisters. He was the second son. He came to Hawaii with his friends and worked on a sugarcane farm. However, due to unsuccessful farming, he came to Watsonville to join his older brother and a brother-in-law, who were growing strawberries. Their parents arranged their marriage on May 13, 1909. Mrs. Fuji Murakami was born April 21, 1888, also to a farming family in Yamaguchi prefecture. She had four brothers and sisters. Mrs. Murakami is the second daughter. She came to Watsonville when she was 21 years old. They had five children together (two boys and three girls). The grey strawberries in Watsonville. During the war, since all of their children were married and not with them, only Mr. & Mrs. Murakami went to Salinas and then to Poston, Arizona, Camp #2. One son was drafted as a solder, while the other son left early for Chicago. After camp, Mr. and Mrs. Murakami went to Chicago to join their son for two to three years. After that, they returned to Watsonville. They recollect that thanks to the police presence and pro-Japanese American neighbors, their house remained the way it was. They resumed growing strawberries.
    Poston (Ariz.)
    - Interview, May, 1978, 1978-05; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, May, 1978: Interviewee's Copy, 1978-05; 1 audiocassette
    - Transcripts, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 9)
  - 11. Toshi Murata, 1978-05-17 to 1981-01-23; Murata, Toshisuke (Toshi)
    The interviewee’s name is Mr. Toshisuke Murata. Mr. Murata changed his name to “Toshi” Murata when he became a naturalized citizen of the United States. Mr. Toshisuke Murata was born Jan. 10, Meiji 40 (1907) in Hidaka-gun, Hidaka-cho, Ikeda, Wakayama prefecture. His father, Yasutaro Murata, was a rice farmer. His mother’s name is Riki. All together, he has seven brothers and sisters. He was the youngest son. Four of them came to the United States. Mr. Yasutaro Murata arrived first in 1906 or 1907, around the time Mr. Toshi Murata was born. Mr. Yasutaro Murata worked in Castroville, CA as a farmer, growing sugar beets and peas. Mr. Toshi Murata came to the United States in 1921 at the age of 14. He was sent to the Angel Island immigration office and stayed there for one night. Mr. Toshi Murata’s mother never joined her husband and sons in the United States. His older brother, Shigeru, came to the United States four years before Mr. Toshi Murata to join their father. His other brother, Masazo, also joined his father in the United States. Two of four sisters came to the United States and married here. Mr. Toshi Murata’s father returned to Japan in 1923. After that, his brother and Mr. Toshi Murata moved to Watsonville to join their other relatives. He was only 16 or 17 at the time, but already determined to settle in the United States. Mr. Toshi Murata went to Salinas in 1936. Before that, he drove a truck in Watsonville from 1929 to 1932. He married his wife, who was born in Salinas, in 1941 – the year the war started. They don’t have any children.
    When the war began, Mr. and Mrs. Murata, along with Mrs. Murata’s parents, her two sisters and her younger brother, all moved to the temporary camp in Salinas for two months. Then, they moved to Camp #2 in Poston, Arizona. They came back to Watsonville in 1945 and worked in the apple orchards packing fruit. After that, he was employed at a lettuce company. He received his American citizenship in 1952.
    Murata, Masazo; Murata, Riki; Murata, Shigeru; Murata, Yasutaro; Hidaka-chō (Wakayama-ken, Japan); Poston (Ariz.); Salinas (Calif.)
    - Interview, May 17, 1978, 1978-05-17; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, January 19, 1981, 1981-01-19; 2 audiocassettes
    - Interview, January 23, 1981, 1981-01-23; 1 audiocassette
    - Transcripts, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 10)
  - 12. Kokuho Nakamura, 1978-05-07; Nakamura, Kokuho
    Name: Nakamura Kokichi. Place of origin: Kagoshima-ken Kawanabe-gun Chiran-cho Kadonoura. Birthday: Dec. 25, 1898 (Meiji 31).